INSTRUCTOR: Hello, everyone.
And welcome to the content
video for binary search
tree in Python.
OK, so basically in
this content video,
we're going to go over how
to build a binary search tree
and do find and inserts
and deletes in Python.
So that code is in
the GitHub repo.
And there's a couple there.
There's bst.py and then
there's also bst_complete.
So I have a few
programming activities
that are built right
into this program
that you can go through and
do them and practice and learn
how to do it yourself.
And then you can either
check or compare it
with bst_complete, which
is the same file with just
all of those tasks
are completed,
all of those programming
activities are completed, OK.
So let's go through
here, bst.py and talk
about how to implement
a binary search tree.
So one of the things
that's surprising
is how simple it really is.
So the structure
of a binary search
tree, the entire structure
is contained in the nodes.
And the nodes in
this implementation
are lines 23 through 29,
that class node right there.
And that is it.
So what's in that node?
Well, here I have a
constructor, which
creates the key, the left
child, and then the right child,
and that's it.
If the binary search
tree has one item in it,
that's the node it uses.
If it has 1 million nodes
in the binary search tree,
that's all they are.
Well, then how does
it build a tree?
How is the structure held
together and managed together
just with these children?
So let's think
about Python here.
Self.left, when I initialize
it, I make it none or in Python,
none is an object that
basically wraps a null value.
So we just treat none like null.
So we can really think of it in
application like the same thing.
So when I create a new node,
it's got two null children.
If you can see back
on the board there,
any node that doesn't have
another node as a child,
it's null or none.
So when I start with a
node, I make it none.
Well, what does that left and
right child become eventually
when I insert things
into the tree?
It just becomes another
node, that's it.
The left and right children of
a node in a binary search tree
will always be either
a node or a null.
That's it.
So whether this binary search
tree has millions of nodes,
they're all going to either
point to another node
left and right or are null.
And that contains the structure.
I don't need another class to
manage how many levels I have,
although there are
implementations
that do keep track of how
many levels the tree has.
And there are binary search
trees that are implemented
that rebalance themselves,
which we're not
going to cover into this class.
If you're interested in
those, I can point you
in the right direction
of a class to take.
But all of them come down to the
structure of the binary search
tree is contained in the
nodes themselves, OK.
So then once I have a node,
how do I add new nodes?
How do I find nodes?
How do I delete nodes?
Well, remember, the operations
in a binary search tree
are recursive.
So the logic of inserting a
node into a tree of size 1
or a tree of size 1
million is the exact same.
And so here's the first
one we're going to look at,
the Insert method.
So how can you look at
this and know right away
it's a recursive function?
Well, it's going to
have calls to itself,
and those are on
lines 41 and 43.
And before I get
to the base case,
let's just look at
those really quick.
So on line 40, if key is
less than the node.key,
node.left equals a recursive
call of node.left in the key.
So basically, this means when
I'm looking to insert something,
if it's smaller than the current
key I'm at, I go to the left.
If it's greater than the current
key I'm at, I go to the right.
And what do I mean,
go to the right?
That's a generic term.
What does that mean?
It means make a recursive
call to the left.
Give it node.left the next
node to visit and the key
I'm trying to insert.
That's what I mean by go to
the left or go to the right.
Make a recursive call to the
left and a recursive call
to the right.
Well, these are
Python functions.
They will return something.
What do I want them to return?
I want them to return
the node when it's done.
So now, let's look
at the base case here
of this recursive function.
If the node is none,
return node of key, OK.
Let's break this logic
apart a little bit.
If the node is none,
well, that just
means I got down to the two--
I got down far enough in the
tree to where I hit a null.
Well, when you're inserting,
if you hit a null,
you found the spot
to insert that node.
You found it, you're done.
So what am I going
to return back to?
I return a true.
Hey, I found the spot.
No, you need to insert this node
in there, so it stays in there.
So the structure is updated.
Well, how the heck
do you do that?
By returning a new node.
So here, this node right
here calls a constructor,
it gives it the key, and
this returns a new node.
Well, where does
it return it to?
It returns it to wherever you--
whatever node you came from.
So if I traversed to
the left from a node,
I called this function,
insert node.left key.
Well, then I hit my null.
I return the new node back here.
And then check out
this assignment.
These assignments on
lines 41 and 43 are all--
this is where the complete
restructuring of a binary search
tree is done in
these assignments.
The left child of
that node becomes
whatever's returned from here.
Well, if I just hit a null
and return back a new node,
now, that new node is the
left child of its parent node.
And that's it.
That's how the new node
is stuck into the tree
through that assignment.
And then the tree structure
is updated and we're done.
So after that is done,
it returns back the node.
Well, what's that
node going to be?
It's going to be that
node returns back
to its parent, which returns
back to its parent, which
returns back to its parent.
And then you're done
once you get to the root.
Well, all those returning,
will that mess up the structure
of the tree?
No, because all it's doing is
just returning the child node
to its parent.
There's no assignment here,
if I'm returning a child
to its parent.
All the assignment was
done after I hit the null.
I hit a null, I
restructure the tree,
and I just return it all back
to the root, and I'm done.
And that's it.
That's it.
And that works, if the
tree is size 1 or the tree
is size 1 million.
And that's the insert.
OK, so then, find, how are
we going to find these?
Well, before finding
the minimum-- the tree,
in fact, if you look at
a BST, finding a minimum
is actually pretty simple.
You just go to the left.
So you start at the root.
You just go to the left, go
to the left, go to the left,
go to the left until
you hit a null.
Then once you hit a null, you
know, OK, I'm at my minimum.
Because if I keep
going to the left,
the very last thing I
run into before null
is going to be the smallest key.
So find min and find max are
actually easily implemented
in a while loop because you just
go to the left over and over
and over and over until you
hit null and you found it.
So let me show you
that really quick.
So again, the solution
is in bst_complete,
I'm going to come over
here really quick.
So you can just while loop it.
So here's what I'm do.
I'm going to compare the find
min and the find min recursive.
And you can decide for yourself
which one you think is easier.
So here's the find min
that's not recursive.
This is just a while loop.
And when I while loop,
how do I go down?
I'm using that language,
like go down the tree.
Well, how do you
do that in code?
Well, here it is.
You while loop, while note.left
is not none, meaning I
haven't hit a null
yet on my left.
I make the node.left
my new node.
So that little assignment there
basically says the left child,
that's now your new node.
And then you while loop again.
Well, does my current node have
a left child that's not none?
If it's not known,
it means it's a node.
Then you go to that one.
How do you go there?
By assigning node
equals node.left where
my child node is now my node.
And you just do
that over and over
and over, making the
left child the new node,
the left child is the new node,
the left child is the new node
until you hit a none.
Then this while loop will break,
and you're at the smallest node.
OK, now, let's take a look at
the recursive solution here.
So the recursive solution--
and actually, I need to
make a quick change here.
That's right, I can change
it, and you can watch.
All right, so we have our
find min recursive here.
A quick pause there, I had
to turn the lights back on.
OK, so I've got my
find min recursive.
Well, my base case is identical
to the clause and the while
loop.
When I finally get down to
where my left node is a none,
I found the smallest, return it.
I can see one little
mistake here though.
Well, I'm going to
return node.left,
actually, this is
recursive, so I need
to return a recursive call.
So it's going to be find
min recursive, node.left.
There we go.
Now, it's fixed.
So if I don't hit a
null yet, what do I do?
I recall find min recursive
and give it my left child
as my new node.
Because my left child,
I know it's not none,
I just checked for that.
So now, I make a recursive
call down to the left
and then I call-- and
then I check again.
Is my node.left none?
Let's say, it's not.
No, it's not.
Then I make a function
call to the left.
Is it none?
No, function call to the left.
And finally, when it
is, when I finally hit
the none where I've got to the
minimum, then I return the node.
Well, that node is
going to get returned
to the previous
function call, which
is going to get returned to the
previous function call, which
is going to get returned
to the previous function
call all the way back until
the root node and the original
find min recursive.
And that's it.
So again, a recursive solution--
excuse me, a
recursive problem is
when the solution
to the superset
is the same as the
solution to the subset,
meaning here in this tree,
this four lines of code
is the exact same no matter
if the superset of the tree
is 1 million nodes
or if it's 1 node.
It works for any size tree.
And that includes
subtrees inside a tree.
As I go up and down the tree
and go through subtrees,
it's the same exact logic.
So that's another reason
recursive solutions are
very popular with trees is
because once you solve it
for one node, you don't have
to touch the code again.
OK.
Then on line 60, I
find max recursive
is the same exact thing, except
I just check on the right.
If my node right is
not none, then I'm
going to go to the
right with a function
call all the way
down till it is.
And then return back,
and I found my node, OK.
And I'm going to get to printing
a tree through in-order,
pre-order, and post-order.
In fact, I'll end on
traversing a tree.
Let's go through finding
and deleting a node first.
So finding a node is
recursive as well.
You just go to the left or
it's all based on the key,
The key you're
searching for, you
compare it with the
key of where you're at.
And go to the left, go to
the right, go to the left,
go to the right
through recursive calls
until you found it.
So the base case is--
the base case is,
if my key matches--
excuse me, if my search
key matches my root key,
I found it, OK.
And I could have put that
base case at the top,
but it worked well on
an if else right here.
So I'll just-- let's start
with the else right here.
If my search key is not
less than or not greater
than the root key, then
I know I've found it.
And I return my string here.
I found the key.
And really, this could
just be a true or false.
But here, it just
prints, it found the key.
So effectively, the same thing.
But then what about
these if statements?
Well, if the search
key I'm looking for
is less than the root, that
means I need to go to the left.
So look at my
recursive call here.
Go to the left and add
the search key right here.
So now, I go to the
left with a search key
and do this logic again.
Well, if the search key is
greater than the root key,
then I do the same thing,
but I make a function call
to the right.
And that's it.
And let me point out one
little difference between this
and the previous root here.
Notice the name root.
But this is going
to change each time.
So root node might have
been a little bit better
of a variable name,
although calling it
a root node, even when you're
using recursion is very common.
But just keep in mind, the
first time I call find key,
it's going to take
the root of the tree.
But then as it recurses
down, root.key key each time
is just going to be
the node you're at.
Think of it like the
root of the subtree.
And if you're
thinking, well, that's
confusing, why don't you
just call it the node?
Yeah, I agree with you.
But root, just as you go down
and down and down looking
for that key, that's
what root is, OK.
And then delete node, the
code gets a little bit longer,
but it's really the
exact same as a find.
It just recurses down
until it finds it.
And then again,
the only difference
here is it needs to replace
the node it deleted to keep
the structure of the tree.
And it does that by finding
the minimum in the right.
Here, it uses the find minimum.
It goes and says, give me the
find min of my right subtree,
and that's going to be the one
I replace this one with here.
But as you may
recall, you could also
use the find max
in my left subtree.
They would both effectively
do the same thing.
And that's really it, all right.
That is find, inserts, and
deletes in a binary search tree.
Let me just run it really
quick, and we'll take a look.
And then lastly, we're going to
talk about traversing a tree,
OK.
So here, you can take a look.
Here's our tree down here.
I should also mention, if you're
looking at the code in my GitHub
repo, there's one
file I included
that makes your life
a lot easier when
you're working with trees.
It's print tree.
Because if you just print
out the items in a tree one
by one on a straight
line, then you
need to keep track
of how you traverse
that tree to get the order of
the numbers that were printed.
This print_tree.py gives you
a nice visual representation
of the tree, if you can see
where I'm highlighting right
here.
And that's really
nice to keep track
of the structure
of your tree, OK.
So that's printing entry.
And then lastly, let's talk
about traversing a tree.
So as we're going,
let's say you want
to visit all of the
nodes in the tree,
either to print all of the nodes
or to perform an operation tree
store data.
So the operation
could be find me
the average of all the nodes or
whatever statistical information
you're looking for of
all the nodes in my tree.
But you need to go through
everything in the tree.
So the tree traversals I'm
going to talk about next refer
to traversing the entire tree.
Well, there's actually
a few ways to do that.
So the operation
example I used of a sum
or a mean, median, mode, you're
looking for through the data
of your tree.
So I'm going to use the
example here, though, of print.
So here, I'm not performing
a mathematical calculation,
although I could, here, I'm just
going to print the tree, OK.
So let's talk about in-order.
So when I traverse
in-order, again, I'm
going through the
entire tree here.
In-order traversal does
what its name suggests.
It goes through all
of the keys in order.
And the way it does
that is by recursing
left down the tree, all
of the left subtrees.
Check out line 68 there.
Then it prints the node
it's at, and then it
traverses down to the right.
So it's basically go left,
then perform the operation,
and then go right.
So if you look in my--
let me set this up
a little bit better,
so you can understand it.
So check out lines
193 through 199.
I create a tree
here by adding 314,
and I didn't add the second
one to make a duplicate,
but I could have.
3, 1, 4, 2, 5, 9, OK.
So then I've got my tree, and
you can see that in the output
there.
Check out the
in-order traversal.
All the numbers get
printed out in order,
but I still traverse
the entire tree.
We'll look at the next
one, 3, 1, 2, 4, 5.
That one is done--
let me get to that code,
there we go, pre-order.
So pre-order is
identical to in-order.
But check out the
one difference.
In-order, I do my
operation in the middle.
I traverse left,
perform my operation.
Again, here, I'm
just printing it.
But it could be a mathematical
calculation or anything
you want.
Then I go right.
Pre-order, I do my
operation first.
So what's the first
thing you're always
going to print in a
pre-order traversal?
The root.
Print the root, then
go left, then go right,
and then that prints out.
Look where I'm highlighting in
my output there, 3, 1, 2, 4, 5,
9.
In-order was 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 9.
Pre-order is 3, 1, 2, 3, 5, 9.
And then post-order, as its name
suggests, you go left, go right,
and then print.
So what's going to be
the last thing you print
in a post-order traversal?
The last thing is
going to be the root.
And check that out in my
output there, 2, 1, 9, 5, 4, 3.
So why do you care or when
would you use which one?
Really, if you're doing
just general statistics
about the data in your
tree, probably most common
would be in-order
but not necessarily.
And the logic to each of
them is nearly identical.
It's just what order
you put the operation
you're trying to perform, OK.
And the last thing
I want to show
you-- let me go back
to our outline here
of our content
video outline here.
Here we go.
So we talked about building,
searching, and printing history.
The last thing I
want to talk about
is a list versus a
binary search tree.
In fact, I think what I'm
going to do is-- this content
video has gotten big enough.
I think I'm going to end this
content video here and make
an additional one for comparing
a list versus a binary search
tree.
So we're going to compare, how
much faster are they really?
So if you haven't viewed
that content video yet,
check it out list versus BST.
That concludes
this content video
of implementing a BST in Python.
Thank you for watching.